Guide to the Brooklyn, N.Y., Bureau of Sewers records ARC.235
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 1: Assessment Binders, circa 1859-circa 1962; 44.8 Linear feet in 85 oversize manuscript boxes, 6 record cartons and 3 flat boxes
  - Sub-series 3: Post-Consolidation, circa 1900-circa 1955; 30.6 Linear feet in 71 manuscript boxes and 1 flat box
    - New Lots Binders 676 - 1008, 1909-1911 (Box 75, Folder 1-6)
    - New Lots Binders 1071, 1252 (2 vols), 1912-1914 (Box 74, Folder 2, 3)
    - New Lots Binders 1045 - 1410, 1912-1915 (Box 76, Folder 1-8)
    - New Lots Binders 1411 - 2168, 1915-1927 (Box 77, Folder 1-6)
    - New Lots Binders 2172 - 2715, 1927-1932 (Box 78, Folder 1-4)
    - Ocean Front Binders 1926 - 2005, 1924-1925 (Box 79, Folder 1-8)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2006 - 2077, 1925-1926 (Box 80, Folder 1-7)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2078 - 2147, 1926 (Box 81, Folder 1-7)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2149 - 2217, 1926-1927 (Box 82, Folder 1-8)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2218 - 2326, 1927-1928 (Box 83, Folder 1-9)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2328 - 2411, 1928-1929 (Box 84, Folder 1-9)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2406 (4 folders), 2413 - 2444, 1929 (Box 85, Folder 1-8)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2446 - 2520, 1929 (Box 86, Folder 1-8)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2522 - 2607, 1929-1931 (Box 87, Folder 1-8)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2609 - 2680, 1931-1932 (Box 88, Folder 1-9)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2682 - 2735, 1932-1935 (Box 89, Folder 1-8)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2745, 2759, 1935 (Box 90, Folder 1, 2)
    - Ocean Front Binder 2785 (1 vol of incomplete set), 1937 (Box 91, Folder 1)
    - Ocean Front Binder 2786 (5 vols in 2 boxes), 1937 (Box 92, Folder 1)
    - Ocean Front Binder 2786 (5 vols in 2 boxes), 1937 (Box 93, Folder 1)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2742 - 2787, 1935-1938 (Box 94, Folder 1-7)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2788 - 2841, 1938-1942 (Box 95, Folder 1-7)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2842 - 2890, 1942-1948 (Box 96, Folder 1-6)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2891 - 2935, 1948-1950 (Box 97, Folder 1-5)
    - Ocean Front Binders 2936 - 2967, 2977, 1950-1952 (Box 98, Folder 1-6)
      Binder 2977 includes a map of the Coney Island area.
    - Ocean Front Binders 2968 - 3063, 1951-1955 (Box 99, Folder 1-3)
    - Ocean Front - Brooklyn Binders 3021 - 3057, 1954-1955 (Box 99, Folder 4)
      The "Brooklyn District" documents in this folder relate to those in Sub-series 4.
    - Prospect Heights Binders 227 - 584, 1903-1908 (Box 99, Folder 5, 6)
    - Prospect Heights Binders 600 - 1564, 1909-1918 (Box 100, Folder 1-4)
    - Prospect Binders 1972 - 2756, 1924-1925 (Box 100, Folder 5, 6)
    - Prospect - River Front Binder 2319, 1953 (Box 100, Folder 7)
    - Red Hook Binders 224 - 707, 1903-1909 (Box 101, Folder 1-3)
    - River Front Binder 2990, 1953 (Box 101, Folder 4)
    - Williamsburg Binders 298 - 482, 1905-1908 (Box 101, Folder 5-7)
    - Williamsburg Binder 7--, 1910 (Box 90, Folder 3)
    - Williamsburg Binders 562 - 1503, 1909-1916 (Box 102, Folder 1-6)
    - Williamsburg Binders 1578 - 2011, 1918-1925 (Box 103, Folder 1)
    - Unspecified District Binders 677 - 2853, 1909-1944 (Box 103, Folder 2-5)
  - Sub-series 4: Brooklyn District, circa 1943-circa 1962; 2.5 Linear feet in six manuscript boxes
    In the 1940s, a new local district appears in the collection, referred to as the "Brooklyn District" or as simply "Brooklyn." At some point in time, all assessment binders begin to refer only to Brooklyn and not to the other district names found in the Post-Consolidation Sub-series. These mid-twentieth century binders referring only to Brooklyn comprise this Sub-series.
    The sub-series is arranged in assessment binder number order. One folder in the Post-Consolidation Sub-series includes some documents relevant to Brooklyn District (see folder titled "Ocean Front - Brooklyn Binders 3021 - 3057" in Box 99).
    - Binders 2843 - 2909, 1943-1948 (Box 104, Folder 1)
    - Binder Number Unknown (Contract number 3614), 1949 (Box 104, Folder 2-4)
    - Binder 2929 (2 folders of 3), 1950 (Box 104, Folder 5, 6)
    - Binder 2929 (1 folder of 3), 1950 (Box 105, Folder 1)
    - Binders 2931 - 3019, 1950-1954 (Box 105, Folder 2-6)
    - Binders 3009 - 3070, 1953-1956 (Box 106, Folder 1-7)
    - Binders 3071 - 3120, 1956-1959 (Box 107, Folder 1-5)
    - Binders 3121 - 3172, 1959-1961 (Box 108, Folder 1-6)
    - Binders 3173 - 3206, 1961-1962 (Box 109, Folder 1-6)
  - Sub-series 5: Queens County, 1912-1927; 0.7 Linear feet in two flat boxes
    The series is arranged in chronological order.
    This sub-series includes a small number of assessment binders related to projects in Queens County, including Newtown.
    - Assessment binders, 1912-1922 (Box 16, Item 1-10)
    - Assessment binders, 1923-1927 (Box 17, Item 1-10)
- Series 2: Division of Survey and Design Worksheets, circa 1936-circa 1959; 1.5 Linear feet in five flat boxes
  The series includes worksheets that appear to be block and lot lists preliminary to those used in the assessment binders (series 1, sub-series 3). The worksheets refer to contract number, not assessment binder number. They appear to relate principally to contracts numbered in the 3400-3900 range only. Some of the worksheets concern private sewer contracts. Most of the worksheets have limited information.
  The worksheets were found in a largely disorganized state, though most pages of multi-page woksheets seem to have stayed together. Some effort was made during processing to bring related pages together, but there can be no assurance that this was accomplished.
  - Worksheets, circa 1936-circa 1959 (Box 19, Folder -)
  - Worksheets, circa 1936-circa 1959 (Box 20, Folder -)
  - Worksheets, circa 1936-circa 1959 (Box 21, Folder -)
  - Worksheets, circa 1936-circa 1959 (Box 22, Folder -)
  - Worksheets, circa 1936-circa 1959 (Box 23, Folder -)
- Series 3: Contract Administration Logsheets, circa 1920-1960; 1.5 Linear feet in one record carton, one manuscript box, and one flat box
  The series is arranged in chronological order and by the form and subject matter of the document.
  The series includes several volumes of logsheets in a standard, pre-preprinted form used for recording key dates in the administration of a project (e.g., district resolution passed, approvals received, prints made, property owner lists prepared, etc.). The assessment binder number (see series 1, sub-series 3) to which the contract relates is also recorded. Summary logs are included in the material. One of the volumes relates to private sewer work. There are sizable gaps in the earliest records in the series, and it appears that the earliest forms relate to contract number circa 2100. The series runs through contract 3969. The related assessment binders appear to run circa 1603 to 3157, but there is not a direct correlation in sequence between the contract numbers and the assessment binder numbers.
  The series also includes a "scrapbook" of clippings of published requests for project bids, with annotations, 1923-1932, a log recording the removal and return of project records from the files, 1929-1946, a list of quarterly reports (1933-1940), and lists related to contracts for the Sheepshead Bay area.
  - Contracts circa 2076-2708 (assessments circa 1603-2087), circa 1920-1925 (Box 7, Item 1)
  - Contracts circa 2709-3064 (assessments circa 2068-2411), 1926-1929 (Box 7, Item 2)
  - Contracts circa 3065-3300 (assessments circa 2421-2617), 1929-1931 (Box 7, Item 3)
  - Contracts circa 3301-3651 (assessments circa 2823-2929), 1931-1950 (Box 7, Item 4)
  - Contracts circa 3651-3773 (assessments circa 2908-3008), 1948-1953 (Box 7, Item 5)
  - Contracts circa 3774-3969 (assessments circa 3124-3157), 1959-1960 (Box 7, Item 6)
  - Private Sewer Contracts 541-785, 1936-1960 (Box 7, Item 7)
  - Document Use Log, 1929-1946 (Box 8, Item 1)
  - Project Bid Requests, 1923-1932 (Box 8, Item 2)
  - Quarterly Reports; Sheepshead Bay Area Sewer Contract Lists, circa 1933-circa 1940 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    The documents in this folder are brittle and crumbling apart. They should be used only with archival supervision.
- Series 4: Project Work Logs and Journals, circa 1909-circa 1940; 1.25 Linear feet in one record carton and one flat box
  The series is arranged in chronological order and by subject of the documents.
  This series includes various types of logs and journals concerning the work performed on projects and the work roles of project participants. The principal documents in the series include: a 4 volume "diary" of daily work performed on contract 1924 in 1915-16 (Tompkins Ave from Greene Ave to Fulton St, etc.) performed by the Litchfield Construction Company, and a 2 volume "Force Acct Book" concerning contract 882 (1909-12) performed by the J.J. Creem(?) Company at East 95th St., between East New York Ave. and Hegaman Ave, etc. The series also includes a notebook referring to various projects (circa 1916-1920s), and logs of work assignments (circa 1930s-1940).
  - Work Logs and Journals, circa 1909-circa 1940 (Box 11, Item 1-8)
  - Work Logs and Journals, circa 1909-circa 1940 (Box 12, Item 1-3)
- Series 5: Land Valuation Assessments, 1932-1938, 1951; 0.5 Linear feet in six folders in one record carton (Box 9, Folder 6 folders)
  The series includes correspondence, maps, blueprints, computations, and other documents related to the design engineer's determination of the assessed valuation of land within a project area.
  The series is arranged in order of a code found on the correspondence, which runs in roughly chronological order. Codes found in the series range from 8601 to 8759.
  - Assessments, 1932-1938, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 6 folders)
- Series 6: Blueprints, Bulk, 1914-1927; circa 1897-circa 1935; 2.0 Linear feet in two record cartons
  The series was minimally processed and there is no order to the material.
  The series includes blueprints for tunnels, regulators, sewer and manhole placement on streets and at railroad crossings, technical details of sewers, and other related matter. Much of the material is labeled as being either a superseded plan or as a plan having no special structure. Some specific structures included are plans for a "biological plant" in the 26th Ward and a 1907 tunnel for improving the sanitary conditions of the Gowanus Canal.
  The plans are printed on cloth, folded, with pencilled descriptions on the backing.
  - Blueprints, circa 1897-circa 1935 (Box 13, Folder -)
  - Blueprints, circa 1897-circa 1935 (Box 14, Folder -)
- Series 7: Field Books - Special Sewer Structures, circa 1929; 0.5 Linear feet in one manuscript box
  The series is ordered according to the numbers on the booklets (1-30, except for 27, which is missing), preceded by two unnumbered booklets (an index and a table of inspections).
  The series includes a set of booklets with field notes and drawings concerning special sewer structures.
  - Field Books, circa 1929 (Box 15, Item 31 booklets)
- Series 8: Tests and Computations, 1906-1910, circa 1930s; 1.0 Linear feet in one record carton
  The series is arranged chronologically and by subject of document.
  The series includes several bound volumes of results of tests of construction materials and of construction-related computations, circa 1906-1910. One folder, possibly circa 1930s, includes various lists of information, including locations of overflow manholes, drop manholes, and "unusual and extraordinary types of sewer construction," and other items.
  - Tests and Computations, 1906-1910, circa 1930s (Box 10, Item 1-9)
- Series 9: Excavation Notices, Bulk, 1988; 1986-1988; 0.4 Linear feet in six folders in one record carton
  The series is in chronological order by year. Within years, there is no order.
  This series includes "Notices of Excavation and/or Demolition" filed under Rule 53 of the Industrial Code. The bulk of the series includes forms from 1988, with some from 1987 and a very few items from 1986. The notices follow a standard form and include information about the excavator and the location (e.g., address) and brief description of the work to be done.
  - Notices, 1986-1988 (Box 9, Folder 6 folders)
- Series 10: Miscellaneous, 1853-circa 1954; 0.1 Linear feet in four folders in one record carton
  The series includes various items that did not fit within the scope of the other series. There is no order to their presentation.
  This series includes a variety of a small number of documents that did not fit well within the other series of the collection. The series includes two contracts from the 1850s for sewerage work (one in Navy St. from DeKalb to Flatbush Ave. and the other concerning sewers in District 6 commencing at North Second St.), a draft contract, 1902 correspondence concerning a troublesome employee, addenda to specifications for a pumping station at Avenue V, and an advertising piece for Andrews Pressure Water Supply. A large number of blank forms were found with the original collection. The bulk of these were discarded, but a sample was retained in this series (blanks of the oversize forms used by the Division of Survey and Design as worksheets are found in that series).
  - Miscellaneous, 1853-circa 1954 (Box 9, Folder 4 folders)